Finding Aid for John R. Dethmers papers, 1923-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John R. Dethmers papers 1923-1970
Dethmers, John R., 1903-1971.
851084 Aa 2
Prosecuting attorney, attorney general of Michigan, 1945-1946, and justice on the Michigan Supreme Court, 1946-1970. Correspondence and campaign material relating to his political interests, court agendas and topical files, and papers relating to the operation and activities of the state supreme court; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
11 linear feet
The collection was the gift of Judge John R. Dethmers (donor no. 4283 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
A native of Plessis, Iowa, John R. Dethmers came to Michigan in 1921 at the age of 18. He attended Hope College in Holland, was a 1927 graduate of the University of Michigan law school and subsequently received law degrees from Detroit College of Law and Hope.
He practiced law in Zeeland from 1927 to 1932 and also served as city attorney. He was named Ottawa County prosecuting attorney in 1930, serving four terms. Then he practiced law in Holland from 1932 to 1944. Dethmers was president of the Michigan Prosecuting Attorneys Association in 1937-38 and served as Republican State Chairman in 1942-45.
Dethmers was chief assistant attorney general in 1943-44 before being elected attorney general in 1944. He was appointed to the supreme court in 1946. He served as chief justice of the court twice, from 1956 to 1962 and from 1967 to 1971 He died November 1, 1971.
This collection of John R. Dethmers papers, in addition to a few folders of correspondence and campaign materials from the 1930s, is comprised mainly of files from his service on the Michigan Supreme Court. Within the Correspondence series, there are letters from William W. Blackney, Mar. 19, 1942; Fred Bradley, Mar. 4, 1942; Albert J. Engel, Mar. 2, 1942; Bartel J. Jonkman, Mar. 6, 1942; Earl C. Michener, Mar. 2, 1942; Chase S. Osborn, Mar. 16, 1942; and Arthur H. Vandenberg, Mar. 4, 1942.
Subjects:
Dethmers, John R., 1903-1971.; Judges--Michigan.; Law.; Lawyers--Michigan.; Michigan. Dept. of Attorney General.; Courts--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Republican Party (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dethmers, John R., 1903-1971.
Contributors:
Blackney, William Wallace, 1876-1963.; Bradley, Frederick Van Ness, 1898-1947.; Engel, Albert Joseph, 1888-1959.; Jonkman, Bartel J. (Bartel John), 1884-1955.; Michener, Earl C. (Earl Cory), 1876-1957.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1929-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942 (Box 1)
- Political materials and early career
  - National Republican campaign material 1932-1940 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Republican campaign material 1934-1942 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Democratic campaign material 1935-1938 (Box 1)
  - Political miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Personal political miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Bulletins of the Muskegon Merchants' Service Bureau and the Zeeland Retailer's Credit Association 1928 (Box 1)
- Michigan Supreme Court
  (include some files from his work as Michigan Attorney General)
  - Agendas of the monthly conferences of the justices
    - February 1965-May 1967 (Box 1)
    - June 1967-December 1968 (Box 2)
    - January 1969-November 1970 (Box 3)
  - Topical file 1967-1970
    The files are arranged alphabetically. There is at present no folder listing.
    - A-Detroit Riot (Box 3)
    - District Courts-M (Box 4)
    - N-Z (Box 5)
  - Investigation of the administration of the Jackson Prison 1945-1946 (Box 5)
  - Assignment of Eugene Huff to the 3rd Circuit Court 1958 (Box 5)
  - Annual Conference of Chief Justices 1952-1959 (Box 6)
  - Office of the Court Administrator
    - Memos 1964-1970 (Box 6)
  - Papers 1964-1970 (Box 7)
  - Budgets of the Supreme Court 1958-1963 (Box 7)
  - Probate courts materials 1967-1970 (Box 7)
  - Annual Michigan Judicial Conferences
    - 1958-1961 (Box 8)
    - 1964-1970 (Box 9)
  - Proposed changes in court rules 1964-1970 (Box 10)
  - Proposed changes in court rules 1964-1970 (Box 11)
  - Miscellanea 1953-1969 (Box 11)
  - Photographs (Box 11)
Related Material
The library also has a collection of John R. Dethmers personal papers. The collections have been kept separate at the request of the donor.